Guide to the Carl T. Schofer Diaries, 1897-1918 AIS.2019.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Carl T. Schofer Diaries
1897-1918
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Schofer, Carl T. (Carl Theodore), 1860-1920
AIS.2019.10
0.63 Linear Feet
Carl T. Schofer (1860-1920) was a German-born fresco artist and designer. After immigrating to Brooklyn, NY and working in Buffalo, NY, and Chicago, IL, he settled in Pittsburgh, PA, where he began recording his work in this collection of eighteen diaries.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acqusition Information
Acquired through Dan Casavant Rare Books, August, 2019.
Arrangement
The Schofer diaries consists of eighteen volumes that are arranged chronologically.
Biography/History
Carl Theodore Schofer (1860-1920) was a mural and fresco artist who worked as a decorator in Buffalo, Chicago, and Pittsburgh.
Schofer was born in Pforzheim, Baden, (now Germany) on May 15, 1860 to August Schofer and Katherina Morlock Schofer. After completing trade school in Stuttgart, Baden-Wurttemberg. He immigrated to the United States and resided in Brooklyn, NY in 1881 where he began designing sketches for structure paintings. He relocated to Buffalo, NY and Chicago, IL for work and eventually settled in Pittsburgh, PA in 1902, where he lived and worked the remainder of his life.
Known for his fresco work, art panels, stenciling, lettering, linoleum, and other interior architectural decoration, Schofer earned a living painting and decorating residential, commercial and public buildings. He was a member of the Associated Artists of Pittsburgh and is referenced in many period art journals including: the American Art Directory, American Art Annual and International Studio. He was a member of The Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators and Paperhangers of America, Local Union # 84. In 1914, Schofer was among more than 60 artists to exhibit at the Frederick Galleries in Pittsburgh in the Spring Show.
His work on residential properties represents several high-profile homes throughout Pennsylvania, Illinois, and Michigan. In Pittsburgh, his residential projects included the Eberhardts, Childs, Shields, Kaufmann and Mellon homes. He spent five months working in Dearborn, Michigan on Fairlane, the estate of Henry and Clara Ford (Clara is mentioned often in the 1915 diary) and in Moline, Illinois he worked on the home of John Deere.
Commercial and public projects that Schofer worked on includes: the William Penn Hotel, Fort Pitt Hotel, Carnegie Libraries, City-County Buildings, Union Trust Building, Jenkins Arcade, and buildings at the new Carnegie Tech School (later Carnegie Mellon University). He also worked on projects at what would become Colonial Williamsburg (Va.).
While in Chicago, Schofer married Clara Linhorl in 1884. The Schofer's were the parents of three children: Clara (1884), Erwin (1886), and Martha (1888). Erwin appears to have followed his father in the business of decorating and mural painting. After moving to Pittsburgh, they resided in the Mount Washington neighborhood of Pittsburgh and later in the Borough of Crafton.
Carl T. Schofer died at the age of 60 years on December 4, 1920 of Pneumonia at Mercy Hospital in Pittsburgh. The Schofer's are buried at the Mount Lebanon Cemetery, located in Mount Lebanon, Allegheny County, Pennsylvania.
Related Material
Schofer Family Papers and Photographs, 1880s-1970s, MSS 748, Thomas and Katherine Detre Library and Archives, Senator John Heinz History Center
Records of the Associated Artists of Pittsburgh, 1910-2013, MSS #399, Historical Society of Western Pennsylvania
Eberhardt and Ober Brewing Company Records, 1883-1897, AIS.1994.07, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Henry Clay Frick Business Records, 1862-1987, AIS.2002.06, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Jenkins Arcade and Empire Building, Pittsburgh, Pa. and the Empire Hotel, New York, N.Y., Collection of Plans and Drawings 1897-1953, ais198401, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh
Union Arcade Building Photograph Collection, 1915-1916, AIS.2005.09, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Scope and Content Notes
The Carl Schofer diaries consist of eighteen pocket style diaries dating between 1897 and 1918 that document the professional work of the mural painter, decorator, and stenciler, Carl Theodore Schofer. His projects included work in residential, commercial, and public buildings. Commercial work includes banks, restaurants, theaters, hotels, fraternal and union clubs, libraries, opera houses, concert halls and billiard rooms. Some of his projects included preparations in Buffalo, NY the 1901 Pan American Expo World's Fair. One volume entitled "Europe Trip" documents his travel back to his native Germany.
Artistic techniques mentioned in the diaries include cutting stencils, tapestry patterns for walls, painting ceilings, sketches and designs, and flower painting.
Schofer's projects were located in Buffalo (NY), Chicago (IL), Dearborn (MI), Moline (IL), Pittsburgh (PA), Lawton (OK), Newark (OH), Sonora (PA), Scottdale (PA), and Williamsburg (VA).
Businessmen -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Artists -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Mural painting and decoration; Associated Artists of Pittsburgh; Fair Lane (Dearborn, MI); John Deere House (Moline, IL); Schofer, Carl T. (Carl Theodore), 1860-1920; Ford, Clara Bryant
- Diary, 1897 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  Scope and Contents
  While in Chicago, Schofer's first entries are sketches and pressed leaves. Much of the writing is in Schofer's native German. Writing is illegible in places and details Schofer's work with clients and job descriptions including wages received.
- Diary, 1900 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  Schofer writing includes pressing leaves and descriptions of his jobs at the time, including the Deere's in March through June. Some passages are written in German and names can be deciphered as he continues to track his projects, income, expenses, and a couple of freehand sketches.
- Diary, 1901 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  The diary includes periodicals pressed between the pages. Schofer continues to write partially in German and provides detail of his finances.
- Diary, 1902 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  Schofer, now located in Pittsburgh, details his various travels and activities, including Pittsburgh's Bijou Theater. Mention of the name Clara indiciates that he might have still been working for the Fords. In May, he traveled to West Virginia and is conducting regular work around the region.
- Diary, 1906 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  The diary includes several USPS receipts, one clearly marked for commission. Schofer details his time at each of his projects, including "8 h in Oliver's library ceiling". There is also mention of potential work at the Lyric Theater in Mobile, AL, Clara in NY, and mention of Forbes for a school painting. The diary also includes detail of Schofer's finances.
- Diary, 1907 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  Many of the jobs detailed in the diary are in Pittsburgh area as well as an entry detailing work in Chautauqua. The diary also details time spent on jobs for Mellon family in April. Client addresses and finances are also detailed.
- Diary, 1908 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  In the diary, Schofer spent extensive time at the Ewing residence and travels more frequently to Chicago as well as the Prince Opera House in Houston, TX. He also begins work on his own home. The diary also includes detail of finances and income.
- Diary, 1909 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  This diary contains detail of Schofer's his work throughout the Pittsburgh area as well as a periodical clipping related to the Pittsburgh industrialists. He continues to maintain detail of client addresses and finances.
- Europe Diary, 1909 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  From July 2nd through August 26th, Schofer documents his travels through Europe, mostly writing in his native German. Traveling from Hamburg to Berlin to his hometown of Pforzheim Baden, he sketches and notes the "Regenwetter" through Germany to Holland while collecting names and addresses along the way.
- Diary, 1910 (Box 1, Volume 10)
  The diary includes an almanac with markings made by Schofer, possibly indicating his travel for work or leisure during this time. Beginning in February, the diary contains extensive notes of his work in the Mellon residence. The diary also includes personal drawings and detail of Schofer's finances.
- Diary, 1911 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  The diary contains two newspaper from February 1911, with the rest of writing detailing his projects, including work Pittsburgh's Kleman Hotel and various residences in Wilkinsburg and Uniontown, PA. The diary also tracks finances and names of Schofer's various clients.
- Diary, 1912 (Box 1, Volume 12)
  The diary details Schofer's work on a church in Carnegie, PA and St. Patrick's Church in Gallitzin, PA. An entry on April 15th includes a sketch of a fresco and deeply colored clouds indicating the weather on May 11th. Schofer's project supply costs and income are also recorded in the diary.
- Diary, 1913 (Box 1, Volume 13)
  The diary details Schofer's work across the country, including projects in Chicago, a Presbyterian church in McDonald, PA and the former Broadway venue the Empire Theater. The diary also details Schofer's supplies costs and project income.
- Diary, 1914 (Box 1, Volume 14)
  The diary includes several loose items, including a clipping from a German periodical, a USPS receipt addressed to Richard Schofer, a photograph of his own described watercolor as well as his bookplate. Schofer also documents his time frescoing a bathroom and non-specific eight hours "at my own residence" and his "new residence, Harris Terrace".
- Diary, 1915 (Box 1, Volume 15)
  The diary contains newspaper clippings relating to serums for tuberculosis in Schofer's native Germany and other political clippings written in English. The diary includes a an image of war criminal Karl von Bulow. Schofer resided between Detroit and Dearborn, MI for his projects during this time, and he wrote extensively on designing Henry and Clara Ford's new residence in Detroit, MI. It is possible his wife Clara participated in a women's suffrage event in Pittsburgh similar to the NYC parade on October 23rd, 1915 but incomplete portions of writing makes the events unclear.
- Diary, 1916 (Box 1, Volume 16)
  The diary contains more political newspaper clippings, a record of time spent on projects each day, as well as a collection of addresses in the back. The diary also contains a list of social parties, suggesting Schofer's political engagements.
- Diary, 1917 (Box 1, Volume 17)
  The diary contains newspaper clippings regarding politics of the time along with sketches surrounding significant events of World War I, including the death of Ferdinand Zeppelin on March 8, the U.S. entering war with Germany on April 6th and an event on November 9. Schofer continues recording various projects, including work on the Mellon residence on Woodlawn Road as well as the William Penn Hotel.
- Diary, 1918 (Box 1, Volume 18)
  Schofer continued recording his projects, expenses and saved important newspaper clippings until the end of World War I. Writing in November recount each countries' surrender and the signing of the Armistice is written in bold. The days following contain several more sketches.